Finding Aid for Anna Botsford Bach Home records, 1909-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Anna Botsford Bach Home records 1909-2007 1988-2003
Anna Botsford Bach Home
2 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
05119 Bb 2; UBBm
Ann Arbor retirement home for women; administrative records and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated to the library by the Anna Botsford Bach Home (donor no. 9600 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 2005.
The record group is open to research.
The idea for starting an "Old Ladies' Home" in Ann Arbor began on October 16, 1900 when members of the Charitable Union, a philanthropic organization, gathered together to discuss the number of elderly women with few resources who had been appealing to the organization for aid. Mrs. W.W. Westmore of Ann Arbor was appointed president of the association responsible for raising the funds for this project, but within the year she stepped down and was succeeded by Anna Botsford Bach who helped establish and run the home for the next 15 years.
The home opened on November 16, 1909 with the purpose of providing "a home for older women and to conserve their health, comfort, and happiness." In 1927 the organization moved to the historic Robert Mackenzie House which sits on four acres in West Liberty Street on Ann Arbor's Old West Side. Operating out of this building the Anna Botsford Bach home was able to provide a home for up to sixteen women at a time. The Home continued operating in this location until it closed in 2001.
The Anna Botsford Bach Home record group contains materials from as early as 1909, but the bulk of the records dates to the 1990s. The record group is divided into two series, Administrative records and Photographs.
Subjects:
Anna Botsford Bach Home.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Old age homes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Older women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative records consist of operational and legal files relating to the administration of the Home. Included are board meeting minutes and reports dating from 1970 to 2002. These document the monthly board meetings in the last decade of the organization's existence giving insight into the daily running of the organization as well as a hint of the personal lives of the women living in the home. This series also includes other records of note, such as those relating to the designation of the Robert Mackenzie Home (which long housed the Anna Bach Home) as part of the Ann Arbor Historic District and a scrapbook kept by the organization and containing clippings dating from the Home's beginning in 1909.
  - Admission agreements (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Community Foundation, 2003-2007 (Box 1)
  - Antique inventory and appraisal, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Application for Admission, 1950s-1970s (Box 1)
  - Architectural Plans/Title Abstract (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation, copies 1932-2000 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - Meeting Minutes
      - 1970-1981 (Box 1)
      - 1988-1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994-2001 and 2003 (Box 1)
    - Reports to the Board, 1992-2002 (Box 1)
    - Rosters and Committees (Box 1)
  - By-laws (Box 1)
  - Certificates and Licenses (Box 1)
  - Clippings and Pamphlets (Box 1)
  - Employee Handbook and Job Descriptions (Box 1)
  - Financial Information, 1975-2001 (Box 1)
  - Harriet Swift Bequest Information (Box 1)
  - Historic District Designation (Box 1)
  - Internal Revenue Service and tax exemption (Box 1)
  - Inventory and Appraisal (with photographs) (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents and Miscellaneous Records (Box 1)
  - Michigan Solicitation Licenses, 1976-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Name change (Box 1)
  - Old Ladies Home Trust (Box 1)
  - Property tax exemption (Ann Arbor) (Box 1)
  - Real Estate Appraisal (Box 1)
  - Records of Residents (Box 1)
  - Resident Admission Information and Forms (Box 1)
  - Sale of Property, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1909-1942 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Tax Information (Return of Private Foundation), 1976-2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Trust Agreement Information (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Historical Society (gifts of antiques to the WCHS) (Box 2)
  - Year End Reports 1976-1996 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series is comprised mostly of photo albums and loose photographs documenting special programs held by the Home during the 1990s.
  - Photo Album, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Photo Album, 1998-2001 (Box 2)
  - Photo Album, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Ice Cream Social (Box 2)
  - Loose Photographs, 1990s-2002 (Box 2)
  - Photographic Negatives, 1990-2003 (Box 2)
  - Group photo of residents, ca. 1990 (Folder 1)
  - Historic District Recognition, 1989 (Folder 1)